<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-bfd-yang-06.txt" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BFD YANG">YANG Data Model for Bidirectional Forwarding
    Detection (BFD)</title>

    <author fullname="Reshad Rahman" initials="R." role="editor"
            surname="Rahman">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rrahman@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lianshu Zheng" initials="L." role="editor"
            surname="Zheng">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>vero.zheng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mahesh Jethanandani" initials="M." role="editor"
            surname="Jethanandani">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>mjethanandani@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Santosh Pallagatti" initials="S." surname="Pallagatti">
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>santosh.pallagatti@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Greg Mirsky" initials="G." surname="Mirsky">
      <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>gregimirsky@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="30" month="June" year="2017"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a YANG data model that can be used to configure
      and manage Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD).</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document defines a YANG data model that can be used to configure
      and manage Bidirectional Forwarding Detection <xref
      target="RFC5880">(BFD) </xref>. BFD is a network protocol which is used
      for liveness detection of arbitrary paths between systems. Some examples
      of different types of paths over which we have BFD:</t>

      <t>1) Two systems directly connected via IP. This is known as BFD over
      single-hop IP, a.k.a. <xref target="RFC5881">BFD for IPv4 and IPv6
      </xref></t>

      <t>2) Two systems connected via multiple hops as described in <xref
      target="RFC5883">BFD for Multiple Hops.</xref></t>

      <t>3) Two systems connected via MPLS Label Switched Paths (LSPs) as
      described in <xref target="RFC5884">BFD for MPLS LSP </xref></t>

      <t>4) Two systems connected via a Link Aggregation Group (LAG) interface
      as described in <xref target="RFC7130">BFD on LAG Interfaces </xref></t>

      <t>5) Two systems connected via pseudowires (PWs), this is known as
      Virtual Circuit Connectivity Verification (VCCV) as described in <xref
      target="RFC5885">BFD for PW VCCV </xref>. This is not addressed in this
      document.</t>

      <t>BFD typically does not operate on its own. Various control protocols,
      also known as BFD clients, use the services provided by BFD for their
      own operation as described in <xref target="RFC5882">Generic Application
      of BFD </xref>. The obvious candidates which use BFD are those which do
      not have "hellos" to detect failures, e.g. static routes, and routing
      protocols whose "hellos" do not support sub-second failure detection,
      e.g. OSPF and IS-IS.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="DESIGN-DATA" title="Design of the Data Model">
      <t>Since BFD is used for liveliness detection of various forwarding
      paths, there is no uniform key to identify a BFD session. So the BFD
      data model is split in multiple YANG modules where each module
      corresponds to one type of forwarding path. For example, BFD for IP
      single-hop is in one YANG module and BFD for MPLS-TE is in another YANG
      module. The main difference between these modules is how a BFD session
      is uniquely identified, i.e the key for the list containing the BFD
      sessions for that forwarding path. To avoid duplication of BFD
      definitions, we have common types and groupings which are used by all
      the modules.</t>

      <t>A new control-plane protocol "bfdv1" is defined and a "bfd" container
      is created under control-plane-protocol as specified in <xref
      target="RFC8022">A YANG Data Model for Routing Management </xref>. This
      new "bfd" node is augmented by all the YANG modules for their respective
      specific information.</t>

      <t>BFD can operate in the following contexts: <list style="numbers">
          <t>Network devices as described in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-device-model">Network Device YANG
          Organizational Models</xref></t>

          <t>Logical Network Elements as described in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-lne-model">YANG Logical Network
          Element</xref></t>

          <t>Network instances as described in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-ni-model">YANG Logical Network
          Element</xref></t>
        </list> The approach taken is to do a schema-mount (see <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-netmod-schema-mount">Schema Mount</xref>) of the BFD
      model in the appropriate locations. For example, if an implementation
      supports BFD IP multi-hop in network instances, the implementation would
      do schema-mount of the BFD IP multi-hop model in a mount-point which
      resides in a network instance.</t>

      <t>The data models in this document strive to follow the "Network Management
      Datastore Architecture" (NMDA) guidelines  described in
      <xref target="I-D.dsdt-nmda-guidelines"></xref>. This means that the data
      models do NOT have separate top-level or sibling containers for configuration
      and operational data. One exception at the moment is the model for MPLS-TE
      in <xref target="BFD-MPLS-TE-CFG"></xref></t>

      <section title="Design of Configuration Model">
        <t>The configuration model consists mainly of the parameters specified
        in <xref target="RFC5880">BFD</xref>. Some examples are desired
        minimum transmit interval, required minimum receive interval,
        detection multiplier, etc</t>

        <t>BFD clients are applications that use BFD for fast detection of
        failures. Some implementations have BFD session configuration under
        the BFD clients. For example, BFD session configuration under routing
        applications such as OSPF, IS-IS, BGP etc. Other implementations have
        BFD session configuration centralized under BFD, i.e. outside the
        multiple BFD clients.</t>

        <t>The BFD parameters of interest to a BFD client are mainly the
        multiplier and interval(s) since those parameters impact the
        convergence time of the BFD clients when a failure occurs. Other
        parameters such as BFD authentication are not specific to the
        requirements of the BFD client. To avoid splitting the BFD
        configuration between BFD clients and this centralized model of BFD,
        all the configuration is kept under this centralized model of BFD.
        The only BFD configuration under BFD clients should be an "enable"
        knob which makes those clients react to BFD liveliness detection
        events.</t>

        <section anchor="BFD-COMMON-CFG"
                 title="Common BFD configuration parameters">
          <t>The basic BFD configuration parameters are: <list hangIndent="8"
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="local-multiplier"><vspace/>This is the detection
              time multiplier as defined in <xref
              target="RFC5880">BFD</xref>.</t>

              <t hangText="desired-min-tx-interval"><vspace/>This is the
              Desired Min TX Interval as defined in <xref
              target="RFC5880">BFD</xref>.</t>

              <t hangText="required-min-rx-interval"><vspace/>This is the
              Required Min RX Interval as defined in <xref
              target="RFC5880">BFD</xref>.</t>
            </list>Although <xref target="RFC5880">BFD</xref> allows for
          different values for transmit and receive intervals, some
          implementations allow users to specify just one interval which is
          used for both transmit and receive intervals or separate values for
          transmit and receive intervals. The BFD YANG model supports this:
          there is a choice between "min-interval", used for both transmit and
          receive intervals, and "desired-min-tx-interval" and
          "required-min-rx-interval". This is supported via a grouping which
          is used by the YANG modules for the various forwarding paths.

          For BFD authentication we have: <list hangIndent="8"
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="key-chain"><vspace/>This is a reference to
              key-chain defined in <xref target="RFC8177">YANG Data Model for
              Key Chains </xref>. The keys, cryptographic algotihms, key
              lifetime etc are all defined in the key-chain model.</t>

              <t hangText="replay-protection"><vspace/>This specifies
              meticulous v/s non-meticulous mode as per <xref
              target="RFC5880">BFD </xref>.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IP-SH-CFG" title="Single-hop IP">
          <t>For single-hop IP, there is an augment of the "bfd" data node in
          <xref target="DESIGN-DATA"/>. The "ip-sh" node contains a list of IP single-hop
          sessions where each session is uniquely identified by the interface
          and destination address pair. For the configuration parameters we
          use what is defined in <xref target="BFD-COMMON-CFG"/></t>
          <t><xref target="RFC5880"></xref> and <xref target="RFC5881"></xref> do not
          specify whether echo function is continuous or on demand. Therefore the
          mechanism used to start and stop echo function is implementation specific
          and should be done by augmentation:
          <list>
             <t>1) Configuration. This is suitable for continuous echo function.
                An example is provided in <xref target="ECHO-CONFIG"/>.</t>
             <t>2) RPC. This is suitable for on-demand echo function.</t>
          </list>

          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multi-hop IP">
          <t>For multi-hop IP, there is an augment of the "bfd" data node in
          <xref target="DESIGN-DATA"/>.</t>

          <t>Because of multiple paths, there could be multiple multi-hop IP sessions
          between a source and a destination address. We identify this as a "session-group".
          The key for each "session-group" consists of: <list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="source address"><vspace/>Address belonging to the
              local system as per <xref target="RFC5883">BFD for Multiple Hops
              </xref></t>

              <t hangText="destination address"><vspace/>Address belonging to
              the remote system as per <xref target="RFC5883">BFD for Multiple
              Hops </xref></t>
            </list></t>

          <t>For the configuration parameters we use what is defined in <xref
          target="BFD-COMMON-CFG"/></t>

          <t>Here are some extra parameters: <list hangIndent="8"
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="tx-ttl"><vspace/>TTL of outgoing BFD control
              packets.</t>

              <t hangText="rx-ttl"><vspace/>Minimum TTL of incoming BFD
              control packets.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="BFD-MPLS-TE-CFG" title="MPLS Traffic Engineering Tunnels">
          <t>For MPLS-TE tunnels, BFD is configured under the MPLS-TE tunnel
          since the desired failure detection parameters is a property of the
          MPLS-TE tunnel. This is achieved by augmenting the MPLS-TE data
          model in <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-yang-te">YANG Data Model for TE
          Topologies </xref>. For BFD parameters which are specific to the TE
          application, e.g. whether to tear down the tunnel in the event of a
          BFD session failure, these parameters will be defined in the YANG
          model of the MPLS-TE application.</t>

          <t>On top of the usual BFD parameters, we have the following per
          MPLS-TE tunnel: <list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="encap"><vspace/>Encapsulation for the BFD packets:
              choice between IP, G-ACh and IP with G-ACh as per <xref
              target="RFC5586">MPLS Generic Associated Channel </xref></t>
            </list></t>

          <t>For general MPLS-TE data, "mpls-te" data node is added under the
          "bfd" node in <xref target="DESIGN-DATA"/>. Since some MPLS-TE
          tunnels are uni-directional there is no MPLS-TE configuration for
          these tunnels on the egress node (note that this does not apply to
          bi-directional MPLS-TP tunnels). The BFD parameters for the egress
          node are added under "mpls-te".</t>
        </section>

        <section title="MPLS Label Switched Paths">
          <t>Here we address MPLS LSPs whose FEC is an IP address. The "bfd"
          node in <xref target="DESIGN-DATA"/> is augmented with "mpls" which
          contains a list of sessions uniquely identified by an IP
          prefix. Because of multiple paths, there could be multiple MPLS sessions
          to an MPLS FEC. We identify this as a "session-group".</t>

          <t>Since these LSPs are uni-directional there is no LSP
          configuration on the egress node. </t>
          <t>The BFD parameters for the egress node are added under "mpls".</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Link Aggregation Groups">
          <t>Per <xref target="RFC7130">BFD on LAG Interfaces </xref>,
          configuring BFD on LAG consists of having micro-BFD sessions on each
          LAG member link. Since the BFD parameters are an attribute of the
          LAG, they should be under the LAG. However there is no LAG YANG
          model which we can augment. So a "lag" data node is added to the
          "bfd" node in <xref target="DESIGN-DATA"/>, the configuration is
          per-LAG: we have a list of LAGs. The destination IP address of the
          micro-BFD sessions is configured per-LAG and per address-family
          (IPv4 and IPv6)</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Design of Operational Model">
        <t>The operational model contains both the overall statistics of BFD
        sessions running on the device and the per session operational
        information.</t>

        <t>The overall statistics of BFD sessions consist of number of BFD
        sessions, number of BFD sessions up etc. This information is available
        globally (i.e. for all BFD sessions) under the "bfd" node in <xref
        target="DESIGN-DATA"/> and also per type of forwarding path.</t>

        <t>For each BFD session, mainly three categories of operational items
        are shown. The fundamental information of a BFD session such as the
        local discriminator, remote discriminator and the capability of
        supporting demand detect mode are shown in the first category. The
        second category includes a BFD session running information, e.g. the
        remote BFD state and the diagnostic code received. Another example is
        the actual transmit interval between the control packets, which may be
        different from the desired minimum transmit interval configured, is
        shown in this category. Similar examples are actual received interval
        between the control packets and the actual transmit interval between
        the echo packets. The third category contains the detailed statistics
        of the session, e.g. when the session transitioned up/down and how
        long it has been in that state.</t>

        <t>For some session types, there may be more than 1 session on the
        virtual path to the destination. For example, with IP multi-hop and
        MPLS LSPs, there could be multiple BFD sessions from the source to the
        same destination to test the various paths (ECMP) to the destination.
        This is represented by having multiple "sessions" under each "session-group".</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Notifications">
        <t>This YANG model defines notifications to inform clients of BFD of
        important events detected during the protocol operation. Pair of local
        and remote discriminator identifies a BFD session on local system.
        Notifications also give more important details about BFD sessions;
        e.g. new state, time in previous state, network-instance and the
        reason that the BFD session state changed. The notifications are
        defined for each type of forwarding path but use groupings for common
        information.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="RPC Operations">
        <t>None.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD top level hierarchy">
        <t>At the "bfd" node under control-plane-protocol, there is no
        configuration data, only operational data. The operational data
        consist of overall BFD session statistics, i.e. for BFD on all types
        of forwarding paths. The "bfd" node under control-plane-protocol can
        be used in a network device (top-level), or mounted in an LNE or in a network
        instance.</t>

        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd@YYYY-MM-DD-tree.txt)
                     ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD IP single-hop hierarchy">
        <t>An "ip-sh" node is added under "bfd" node in
        control-plane-protocol. The configuration and operational data for
        each BFD IP single-hop session is under this "ip-sh" node. The "ip-sh"
        node can be used in a network device (top-level), or mounted in an LNE or in a
        network instance.</t>

        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-ip-sh@YYYY-MM-DD-tree.txt)

]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD IP multi-hop hierarchy">
        <t>An "ip-mh" node is added under the "bfd" node in
        cntrol-plane-protocol. The configuration and operational data for each
        BFD IP multi-hop session is under this "ip-mh" node. In the
        operational model we support multiple BFD multi-hop sessions per
        remote address (ECMP), the local discriminator is used as key. The
        "ip-mh" node can be used in a network device (top-level), or mounted in an LNE
        or in a network instance.</t>

        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-ip-mh@YYYY-MM-DD-tree.txt)
                     ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD over LAG hierarchy">
        <t>A "lag" node is added under the "bfd" node in
        control-plane-protocol. The configuration and operational data for
        each BFD LAG session is under this "lag" node. The "lag" node can be
        used in a network device (top-level), or mounted in an LNE or in a network
        instance.</t>

        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-lag@YYYY-MM-DD-tree.txt)
                     ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD over MPLS LSPs hierarchy">
        <t>An "mpls" node is added under the "bfd" node in
        control-plane-protocol. The configuration is per MPLS FEC under this
        "mpls" node. In the operational model we support multiple BFD sessions
        per MPLS FEC (ECMP), the local discriminator is used as key. The
        "mpls" node can be used in a network device (top-level), or mounted in an LNE
        or in a network instance.</t>

        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-mpls@YYYY-MM-DD-tree.txt)
                     ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD over MPLS-TE hierarchy">
        <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-yang-te">YANG Data Model for TE
        Topologies </xref> is augmented. BFD is configured per MPLS-TE tunnel,
        and BFD session operational data is provided per MPLS-TE LSP.</t>

        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-mpls-te@YYYY-MM-DD-tree.txt)
                     ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Interaction with other YANG modules">
        <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-lime-yang-connectionless-oam">Generic YANG
        Data Model for Connectionless OAM protocols </xref> describes how the
        LIME connectionless OAM model could be extended to support BFD.</t>

        <t>Also, the operation of the BFD data model depends on configuration
        parameters that are defined in other YANG modules.</t>

        <section title="Module ietf-interfaces">
          <t>The following boolean configuration is defined in <xref
          target="RFC7223">A YANG Data Model for Interface Management </xref>:
          <list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="/if:interfaces/if:interface/if:enabled"><vspace/>If
              this configuration is set to "false", no BFD packets can be
              transmitted or received on that interface.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Module ietf-ip">
          <t>The following boolean configuration is defined in <xref
          target="RFC7277">A YANG Data Model for IP Management </xref>: <list
              hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
              <t
              hangText="/if:interfaces/if:interface/ip:ipv4/ip:enabled"><vspace/>If
              this configuration is set to "false", no BFD IPv4 packets can be
              transmitted or received on that interface.</t>

              <t
              hangText="/if:interfaces/if:interface/ip:ipv4/ip:forwarding"><vspace/>If
              this configuration is set to "false", no BFD IPv4 packets can be
              transmitted or received on that interface.</t>

              <t
              hangText="/if:interfaces/if:interface/ip:ipv6/ip:enabled"><vspace/>If
              this configuration is set to "false", no BFD IPv6 packets can be
              transmitted or received on that interface.</t>

              <t
              hangText="/if:interfaces/if:interface/ip:ipv6/ip:forwarding"><vspace/>If
              this configuration is set to "false", no BFD IPv6 packets can be
              transmitted or received on that interface.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Module ietf-mpls">
          <t>The following boolean configuration is defined in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-mpls-base-yang">A YANG Data Model for MPLS Base
          </xref>: <list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
              <t
              hangText="/rt:routing/mpls:mpls/mpls:interface/mpls:config/mpls:enabled"><vspace/>If
              this configuration is set to "false", no BFD MPLS packets can be
              transmitted or received on that interface.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Module ietf-te">
          <t>The following configuration is defined in the "ietf-te" YANG
          module <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-yang-te">YANG Data Model for TE
          Topology </xref>: <list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
              <t
              hangText="/ietf-te:te/ietf-te:tunnels/ietf-te:tunnel/ietf-te:config/ietf-te:admin-status"><vspace/>If
              this configuration is not set to "state-up", no BFD MPLS packets
              can be transmitted or received on that tunnel.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA BFD YANG Module">
        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[<CODE BEGINS> file "iana-bfd-types@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/iana-bfd-types@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD types YANG Module">
        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-bfd-types@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-types@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD top-level YANG Module">
        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-bfd@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD IP single-hop YANG Module">
        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-bfd-ip-sh@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-ip-sh@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD IP multi-hop YANG Module">
        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-bfd-ip-mh@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-ip-mh@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD over LAG YANG Module">
        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-bfd-lag@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

  INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-lag@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD over MPLS YANG Module">
        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-bfd-mpls@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-mpls@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="BFD over MPLS-TE YANG Module">
        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-bfd-mpls-te@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-bfd-mpls-te@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Considerations">
        <t>The YANG module defined in this memo is designed to be accessed via
        the NETCONF protocol [RFC6241]. The lowest NETCONF layer is the secure
        transport layer and the mandatory to implement secure transport is SSH
        [RFC6242]. The NETCONF access control model [RFC6536] provides the
        means to restrict access for particular NETCONF users to a
        pre-configured subset of all available NETCONF protocol operations and
        content.</t>

        <t>The YANG module has writeable data nodes which can be used for
        creation of BFD sessions and modification of BFD session parameters.
        The system should "police" creation of BFD sessions to prevent new
        sessions from causing existing BFD sessions to fail. For BFD session
        modification, the BFD protocol has mechanisms in place which allow for
        in service modification.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>The IANA is requested to as assign a new  namespace URI from the
        IETF XML registry.</t>
        <t>This document registers the following namesace URIs in the IETF XML
        registry <xref target="RFC3688"></xref>:</t>
        <t></t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-bfd</t>
        <t>Registrant Contact: The IESG.</t>
        <t>XML: N/A, the requested URI is an XML namespace.</t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t></t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-bfd-ip-sh</t>
        <t>Registrant Contact: The IESG.</t>
        <t>XML: N/A, the requested URI is an XML namespace.</t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t></t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-bfd-mh</t>
        <t>Registrant Contact: The IESG.</t>
        <t>XML: N/A, the requested URI is an XML namespace.</t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t></t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-bfd-lag</t>
        <t>Registrant Contact: The IESG.</t>
        <t>XML: N/A, the requested URI is an XML namespace.</t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t></t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-bfd-mpls</t>
        <t>Registrant Contact: The IESG.</t>
        <t>XML: N/A, the requested URI is an XML namespace.</t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t></t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
        <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-bfd-mpls-te</t>
        <t>Registrant Contact: The IESG.</t>
        <t>XML: N/A, the requested URI is an XML namespace.</t>
        <t>--------------------------------------------------------------------</t>
          <section title="IANA-Maintained iana-bfd-types module">
            <t>This document defines the initial version of the IANA-maintained
               iana-bfd-types YANG module.</t>
            <t>The iana-bfd-types YANG module is intended to reflect the "BFD
              Diagnostic Codes" registry and "BFD Authentication Types" registry
              at https://www.iana.org/assignments/bfd-parameters/bfd-parameters.xhtml
            </t>
          </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Acknowledgements">
        <t>We would also like to thank Nobo Akiya and Jeff Haas for their
        encouragement on this work. We would also like to thank Rakesh Gandhi
        and Tarek Saad for their help on the MPLS-TE model. We would also like
        to thank Acee Lindem for his guidance.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3688"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6020'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6241'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5880'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5881'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5882'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5883'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5884'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7130'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5885'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5586'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8022'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7223'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7277'?>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8040"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-rtgwg-ni-model"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8177"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-teas-yang-te"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-netmod-schema-mount"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-rtgwg-device-model"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-rtgwg-lne-model"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-lime-yang-connectionless-oam"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-base-yang"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.dsdt-nmda-guidelines"?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="ECHO-CONFIG" title="Echo function configuration example">
       <t>The following intervals are added for the echo function (if supported): <list
              hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="desired-min-echo-tx-interval"><vspace/>This is the
              minimum interval that the local system would like to use when
              transmitting BFD echo packets. If 0, the echo function as
              defined in <xref target="RFC5880">BFD </xref> is disabled.</t>

              <t hangText="required-min-echo-rx-interval"><vspace/>This is the
              Required Min Echo RX Interval as defined in <xref
              target="RFC5880">BFD </xref>.</t>
              </list>
              </t>

                      <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/example-bfd-echo@YYYY-MM-DD-tree.txt)
                     ]]></artwork>
        </figure>


      <section title="Example YANG module for BFD echo function">
        <figure align="left">
          <preamble/>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/example-bfd-echo@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>


    </section>
    <section title="Change log">
      <t>RFC Editor: Remove this section upon publication as an RFC.</t>

      <section title="Changes between versions -05 and -06">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Adhere to NMDA-guidelines.</t>

            <t>Echo function config moved to appendix as example.</t>

            <t>Added IANA YANG modules.</t>

            <t>Addressed various comments.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes between versions -04 and -05">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>"bfd" node in augment of control-plane-protocol as per <xref
            target="RFC8022">A YANG Data Model for Routing Management
            </xref>.</t>

            <t>Removed augment of network-instance. Replaced by
            schema-mount.</t>

            <t>Added information on interaction with other YANG modules.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes between versions -03 and -04">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Updated author information.</t>

            <t>Fixed YANG compile error in ietf-bfd-lag.yang which was due to
            incorrect when statement.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes between versions -02 and -03">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Fixed YANG compilation warning due to incorrect revision date
            in ietf-bfd-ip-sh module.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes between versions -01 and -02">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Replace routing-instance, which has been removed from <xref
            target="RFC8022">A YANG Data Model for Routing Management </xref>,
            with network-instance from <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-ni-model">YANG Network Instances</xref></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes between versions -00 and -01">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Remove BFD configuration parameters from BFD clients, all BFD
            configuration parameters in BFD</t>

            <t>YANG module split in multiple YANG modules (one per type of
            forwarding path)</t>

            <t>For BFD over MPLS-TE we augment MPLS-TE model</t>

            <t>For BFD authentication we now use <xref target="RFC8177">YANG
            Data Model for Key Chains</xref></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
